Headmistresses Association of the East Records, 1910-1983
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Headmistresses Association of the East Records
1910 - 1990
Headmistresses Association of the East
MS 369
20 boxes (9.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Professional organization. The purpose of this organization was to provide an opportunity for the furtherance of mutual acquaintance among heads of secondary or elementary schools for the exchange of ideas and advancement of standards. The collection provides insight into the educational and social philosophy of private education in America. Materials include correspondence, proceedings, membership applications, memoranda, and reports.
Historical Note
The Headmistresses Association of the East (HMAE) was founded in 1911 by a group of headmistresses of schools in the Boston, New York, and Philadelphia areas. Agnes Irwin, dean of Radcliffe College, was the first president, serving until her death in 1914. Membership is open to the heads of girls and co-educational schools in New England and in other states on the Atlantic seaboard. The purposes of the organization are "to provide an opportunity for the furtherance of mutual acquaintance among heads of secondary or elementary schools...for the interchange of ideas of common interest or looking toward the advancement of standards...[and to provide] assistance to any head or teacher, active or retired."
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Records of the Headmistresses Association of the East consist of 10 linear feet of correspondence, financial records, proceedings, membership applications, memoranda, and reports. They span the years 1910 to 1983, and provide a good record of the activities of the association as well as insight into the educational and social philosophy of private education in America.
The most informative material is contained is the first three series. There were several by-laws issues regarding a name change to allow headmasters of girls' schools to become active members (the name of the organization remained the same, but the word "head" was substituted in the by-laws). The minutes, agenda, and proceedings contain a complete record of the private and public activities of the HMAE. Among the most important committee activities were the establishment of academic standards for member schools and professional standards for their faculty (especially salary guidelines). In addition the Academic Standards Committee in 1934 requested members to state their educational philosophy. The resulting set of essays, "The Educational Faith That I Hold," provides an interesting historical look at some individual educational philosophies. Through its Irwin Memorial Fund and its Relief of Unemployed Teachers Committee the organization helped needy members, especially in the years before Social Security and school-sponsored retirement programs.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Organization
II. Meetings
III. Committees and Officers
IV. Membership
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
With the exceptions of the Board of Directors minutes and the membership applications, both of which are closed for 40 years from the date of creation, all material is open according to the rules of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
The records were donated in June 1990 through the efforts of Agathe Crouter, headmistress of the Hewitt School and Evelyn J. Halpert, headmistress of the Brearley School and president of the HMAE.
Search Terms
Headmistresses Association of the East--History--Sources; Education--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Private schools--United States--History--Sources; School principals--Organizations--History--Sources; Women--Education--United States--History--Sources
- SERIES I. ORGANIZATION (1910-1970), .12 linear feet
  This series contains incorporation material (1910-14, 1944-54) and constitution and by-laws (1911-70).
- SERIES II. MEETINGS (1910-1980), 4.5 linear feet
  This series contains minutes and agenda of Board of Directors meetings (1911-77) and proceedings, correspondence, and printed material related to the association's annual and biennial meetings (1910-80).
- SERIES III. COMMITTEES AND OFFICERS (1914-1972), 2 linear feet
  This series contains material related to the President and Board of Directors, Secretary, Treasurer, and twenty-two committees that have been active at various times between 1914 and 1972.
  The committees are arranged alphabetically by title.
- SERIES IV. MEMBERSHIP (1914-1983), 3.5 linear feet
  Although membership is personal rather than institutional, the association kept these records by school name. This series contains membership applications and related correspondence for applicants from 126 private schools. These files include supporting information such as personal recommendations, statistics and general information about the schools. There are also some school catalogs.
  The files are arranged alphabetically by school.
  Membership applications less than 40 years old are CLOSED
- SERIES I. ORGANIZATION (1910-1970)
  - Incorporation material, 1910-14, 1944-54 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1911-70 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- SERIES II. MEETINGS (1910-1980)
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Board of Directors: minutes and agenda, 1911-77 (Box 1, Folder 3-10)
    Minutes less than 40 years old are CLOSED
  - Annual and biennial meetings: proceedings, correspondence, printed material
    - 1910-25 (Box 2, Folder 1-12)
    - 1926-37 (Box 3, Folder 1-12)
    - 1938-47 (Box 4, Folder 1-10)
    - 1948-54 (Box 5, Folder 1-7)
    - 1955-59 (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
    - 1960-65 (Box 7, Folder 1-6)
    - 1966-69 (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
    - 1970-80 (Box 9, Folder 1-11)
- SERIES III. COMMITTEES AND OFFICERS (1914-1972)
  - Officers
    - President and Board of Directors: correspondence, memoranda, 1914-71 (Box 10, Folder 1-4)
    - Secretary: duties, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Treasurer
      - Annual financial audits, 1920-72 (Box 10, Folder 6-9)
      - Correspondence, 1944-68 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Committees
    - Instructions for chairmen, members, 1947, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Academic Standards
    - Correspondence, reports, forms, 1934-40, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - "The Educational Faith That I Hold," 1934 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Administrative Problems: report, correspondence, 1937, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Apprentice Teachers: reports, correspondence, 1937, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - By-laws Revision: reports, correspondence, questionnaires, 1945-46, 1965, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - College Board Delegate, 1921-28, 1957-59, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Committee to Study Current Practices in Physical Education and Music: reports, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Fine Arts: reports, questionnaire, 1930-31 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Forms (contracts): correspondence, forms, 1916-44 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Information Blank: forms, reports, 1927-30 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Insurance and Pension: correspondence, 1916 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Irwin Memorial (SEE ALSO Relief of Unemployed Teachers Committee): correspondence, reports, 1915-18, 1939-70, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Joint Committee on Interchange of Teachers: correspondence, reports, 1922-45, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Mathematics Conference: correspondence, reports, 1933-43 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Membership
    - Correspondence, 1919-1976, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 1-6)
    - Reports, miscellaneous, 1920-72, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Nominating: correspondence, miscellaneous, 1919, 1937-57 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Professional Standards
    - Correspondence, 1937-71 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Reports, questionnaires, forms, 1918-24 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Public Issues: report, correspondence, 1918-24 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Public Relations: memoranda, correspondence, 1937, 1947 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Salaries, 1922-26 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Scholarship (mathematics teachers): announcements, statistics, 1954-55, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Study on New Type Examinations in Mathematics: report, correspondence, 1928, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Relief of Unemployed Teachers: correspondence, reports, 1934-66 (Box 13, Folder 9)
- SERIES IV. MEMBERSHIP (1914-1983)
  - Abbot Academy, 1936-72 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Agnes Irwin School, 1940-49, 1962 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Albany Academy for Girls, 1927-42, 1966-70 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Ashley Hall, 1939-50 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Bancroft School, 1938-57 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Barnard School for Girls, 1948-71 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Beard's School, 1929-71 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Beaver Country Day School, 1966-72 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Bergen School, 1954-55 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Berkeley Institute, 1947, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Birch Wathen School, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Bishop's School, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Brearley, 1939-40 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Brimmer and May School, 1942-81 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Brookside School, 1967-73 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Buckingham School, 1936-64 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Buffalo Seminary, 1952-74 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Calhoun School, 1918-69 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Cathedral School of St. Mary, 1935-37 (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Charleton School, 1914 (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Chatham Hall, 1934-71 (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Chestnut Hill School, 1927-34 (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Columbia School, 1938-63 (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Concord Academy, 1940-63 (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Convent of the Sacred Heart, 1970-71 (Box 14, Folder 25)
  - Dana Hall School, 1938-80 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Day Prospect Hill School, 1960-63 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Day School, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Dwight School, 1961-71 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Ellis School, 1971 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Emma Willard School, 1942-74 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Ethel Walker School, 1958, 1972 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Ferry Hall, 1945 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Foxcroft School, 1954-80 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Fox Hollow School, 1970-71 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Garrison Forrest School, 1929-61 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Gill School, 1952-1963 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Girls Latin School, 1930-45 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Greens Farms Academy, 1972 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Greenwich Academy, 1972 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Greenwood School, 1938 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Halsted School, 1942-68 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Hammonasset School, 1972-73 (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Hannah More Academy, 1960 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Hartridge School, 1952 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Hewitt School, 1947-73 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Hewlett School of East Islip, 1966-72 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Holton Arms School, 1930-47 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - House in the Pines, 1919-44 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Howard School for Girls, 1959-65 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Kent Place School, 1926-53 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Kimberley School, 1950-65 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Kingswood School, 1936-50 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Lankenau School, l960 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Laurel School, 1929, 1962 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Lenox School, 1919-58 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Lincoln School, 1930-49, 1953 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Louisville Collegiate School, 1939-49 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Low-Heyward School, 1964 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - MacDuffie School for Girls, 1965-83 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Madeira School, 1913-77 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Maret School, 1950-52 (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Mary C. Wheeler School, 1954-55 (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - Marymount School of New York, 1970-73 (Box 16, Folder 21)
  - Masters School, 1923-71 (Box 16, Folder 22)
  - Meadowbrook School, 1948-49 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Milton Academy, 1928-50 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Miss Fine's School, 1943-44 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Miss Gill's School, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Miss Hall's School, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Miss Hewitt's Classes (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Miss Porter's School, 1953-55 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Moravian Seminary, 1951-68 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Mount Vernon Seminary, 1938-69 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Nashoba Country Day School, 1966-81 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - National Cathedral School, 1950-68 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Nightingale-Bamford School, 1927-71 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Northampton School for Girls, 1927-71 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Northfield Mount Hermon School, 1962-80 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Oldfields School, 1962 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Oxford School, 1942-62 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Phebe Anna Thorne School, 1928 (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Pingree School, 1966-74 (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Potomac School, 1939-75 (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - Professional Children's School, 1948-60 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Prospect Hill Country Day School, 1938-72 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Prospect Hill School, 1937-51 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Riverdale Country School, 1947, 1957 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Rogers Hall, 1942-72 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Roland Park Country School, 1950-75 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Rosemary Hall, 1958-77 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - St. Agnes School Albany, NY, 1930-70 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - St. Agnes School, Alexandria, VA, 1951-77 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - St. Anne's School, 1952-73 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - St. Catherine's School, 1934-65 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - St. Hilda's School, 1954-55 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - St. John the Baptist School, 1950-72 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - St. Katherine's School, 1943 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - St. Margaret's School, Rappahonnock, VA, 1950-51 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - St. Margaret's School, Waterbury, CT, 1950-51 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - St. Mary's Hall, 1953-75 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - St. Mary's in the Mountains, 1946-59 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - St. Mary's School, 1960-72 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - St. Paul's School for Girls, 1975-76 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - St. Timothy's School, 1964 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Salem Academy, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Sandia School, 1941-42 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Sanford Schools, 1964-75 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Seven Hills School, 1971 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Shady Hill School, 1927-63 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Shipley School, 1913-75 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Springside School, 1959-70 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Stevens School, 1954-69 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Stoneleigh-Burnham School, 1969-75 (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Storm King School, 1980 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Stuart Hall, 1955-56, 1972 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Tenacre School, 1944-45 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Town School, 1970 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Tudor Hall School, 1931-41 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Vail-Deane School, 1942-65 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Walnut Hill School, 1953-73 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Westbridge School, 1954 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Westover School, 1964-68 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Williams School, 1978 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Winchester-Thurston School, 1979 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Winsor School, 1916-39 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Wykeham Rise School, 1965-80 (Box 20, Folder 13)